<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2016-02-01 10:03:05"><Identification><BillNumber>C-234</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting the establishment and award of a Living Donor Recognition Medal</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Living Donor Recognition Medal Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2025</YYYY><MM>9</MM><DD>22</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Aboultaif</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2016-02-01">451051</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision first-line-indent="0" subsequent-line-indent="0"><Text>This enactment establishes a medal to be awarded to Canadian citizens and permanent residents who have donated one or more organs in Canada during their lifetime.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas thousands of Canadians are currently awaiting life-saving organ transplants, and the generosity of living donors makes these organ transplants possible through the gift of life;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas living organ donors demonstrate extraordinary compassion, courage and commitment to the well-being of others, often at personal risk and with no expectation of reward;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas these acts of altruism not only save lives but also reduce the burden on the health care system and inspire communities across Canada by embodying the highest values of citizenship and humanity;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament wishes to institute a Living Donor Recognition Medal to recognize and honour the altruistic and life-saving act of living organ donation;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Living Donor Recognition Medal Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions

</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Medal</DefinedTermEn> means the Living Donor Recognition Medal established under section 4.‍ (<DefinedTermFr>médaille</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada designated under section 3. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>organ</DefinedTermEn> includes any form of human tissue. (<DefinedTermFr>organe</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Designation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Minister</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may, by order, designate a member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada as the Minister for the purpose of this Act.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Medal</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Establishment</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>A medal to be called the Living Donor Recognition Medal is established.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Design of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may determine the design of the Medal and its associated ribbon.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Award of Medal</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may award the Medal to any living Canadian citizen or <DefinitionRef>permanent resident</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of subsection 2(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal> who has donated one or more organs in Canada.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Single award</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Medal is not to be awarded more than once to the same person.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Excluded persons</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Medal is not to be awarded to any of the following persons:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a Senator;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a Member of Parliament;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a person excluded by the regulations; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>a person within a class of persons excluded by the regulations.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Awards ceremony</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Text>In order to recognize and promote living organ donation, the Medal is to be presented to the recipient, whenever possible, by a representative of the Crown, a Senator or a Member of Parliament in a public ceremony.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Regulations</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>respecting the process for nominating persons to be considered for award of the Medal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>prescribing persons or classes of persons who are excluded from eligibility for the Medal;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>specifying how the Medal is to be presented; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>providing for the use of post-nominals by recipients of the Medal.</Text></Paragraph></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Prerogative</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Prerogative not affected</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>Nothing in this Act limits the right of the Governor General to exercise all powers and authorities of His Majesty in respect of the Medal.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Report to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Annual report</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Text>Every year, the Minister must prepare a report setting out the number of recipients of the Medal in the previous year and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 sitting days of that House after April 15.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Implementation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Report on implementation</MarginalNote><Label>11</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister must, in consultation with the Office of the Secretary to the Governor General, prepare a report on the implementation of this Act and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 sitting days of that House after the first anniversary of the day on which this Act comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>If no Medals awarded</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If no Medals have been awarded at the time the report is prepared, the report must include reasons for the delay.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>