<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2026-03-19 12:44:57"><Identification><BillNumber>C-281</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Textile Labelling Act and the Consumer Packaging and Labelling Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead /><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>3</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Shipley</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2026-03-19">451162</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Textile Labelling Act</XRefExternal> to provide that Canadian flags that are at least 20 centimetres in width and 30 centimetres in length and that are sold, imported into Canada or advertised must have applied to them a label indicating their country of origin. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Consumer Packaging and Labelling Act</XRefExternal> to provide that the packaging of such flags must also contain a label indicating the flags’ country of origin.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. T-10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Textile Labelling Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Textile Labelling Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 3:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Prohibition respecting the national flag of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>3.1</Label><Text>No dealer shall sell, import into Canada or advertise a consumer textile article that is the national flag of Canada and that is at least 20 centimetres in width and 30 centimetres in length unless the article has applied to it a label containing a representation with respect to its <DefinitionRef>country of origin</DefinitionRef>, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="regulation">Textile Labelling and Advertising Regulations</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-38</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Consumer Packaging and Labelling Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Consumer Packaging and Labelling Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after section 4:</Text><AmendedText><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Prohibition respecting the national flag of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>4.1</Label><Text>No dealer shall sell, import into Canada or advertise any prepackaged product that is the national flag of Canada and that is at least 20 centimetres in width and 30 centimetres in length unless the product has applied to it a label containing a representation with respect to the country of origin of the product.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>