<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2021-11-08 10:22:26"><Identification><BillNumber>C-219</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development Act, the Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law) and the Special Economic Measures Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Sergei Magnitsky International Anti-Corruption and Human Rights Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>International Anti-Corruption and Human Rights Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law No. 3)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>18</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Foreign Affairs and International Development as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on June 18, 2026</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Bezan</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2021-11-08">451061</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development Act</XRefExternal> to impose certain requirements on the Minister of Foreign Affairs in relation to international human rights, prisoners of conscience and human rights defenders.</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</XRefExternal> to provide that</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>transnational repression be sanctioned;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>a copy of each order or regulation made under paragraph 4(1)(b) of the Act must be tabled in each House of Parliament; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>the punishment under paragraph 11(b) of the Act be increased.</Text></Provision><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal> to change that Act’s short title to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Global Sanctions and Special Economic Measures Act (Sergei Magnitski Law No. 2)</XRefExternal>”. It further amends that Act to provide that</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>transnational repression be sanctioned;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>every order or regulation made under paragraph 4(1)(b) of the Act must be tabled in each House of Parliament; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1" language-align="no"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>the punishment under paragraph 8(a) of the Act be increased.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas Parliament supports strengthening Canada’s sanctions regime to better align with ally countries through the imposition of economic measures against a person, entity, foreign national or foreign state <Ins>that has engaged in activities that undermine</Ins> international peace, security <Ins>or stability in a manner inconsistent with international law or who is responsible for, or complicit in</Ins>, gross and systemic violations <Ins>of internationally recognized</Ins> human rights or acts of corruption;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Parliament considers that it is desirable that the Government of Canada continue working with ally countries towards establishing the International Anti-Corruption Court;</Text></Provision><Provision change="ins"><Text>And whereas this Act will enable Canada to impose sanctions on foreign nationals who have engaged in activities that undermine international peace, security or stability in a manner inconsistent with international law or who are responsible for, or complicit in, gross and systematic violations of internationally recognized human rights or acts of corruption;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Anti-<Keep>Corruption</Keep> and Human Rights Act (Sergei Magnitsky <Ins>Law No. 3</Ins>)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2013, c. 33, s. 174</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 10 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Department of Foreign Affairs, Trade and Development Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Human rights</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>In exercising the powers and performing the duties and functions set out in this Act in respect of the conduct of the external affairs of Canada, the Minister must publish, at least once every calendar year, a report that includes an outline of the measures that the Government of Canada has taken to advance human rights — <Ins>and support prisoners of conscience and human rights defenders</Ins> — internationally as part of Canada’s foreign policy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Publication of report</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the first report under subsection (4) within 12 months after the day on which this subsection comes into force.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>prisoner of conscience</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>In this section, <DefinedTermEn>prisoner of conscience</DefinedTermEn> means an individual who, in contravention of international human rights standards, has been detained or otherwise physically restricted solely because of their identity or their conscientiously held beliefs, including religious or political beliefs.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2017, c. 21</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>transnational repression</DefinedTermEn> means tactics used by a foreign state to intimidate, harass, surveil or threaten individuals or groups located outside the state borders or physically harm such individuals or members of such groups, including elected officials, political dissidents, human rights defenders, exiled journalists, diaspora communities, civil society activists and refugees, for the purpose of silencing dissent and stifling activism. (<DefinedTermFr>répression transnationale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label><Ins>(1)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>Paragraph 4(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Ins></Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a foreign national is responsible for, or complicit in, gross violations of internationally recognized human rights;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label><Ins>(2)</Ins></Label><Text>Subsection 4(2) of the Act is amended by striking out “or” at the end of paragraph (c), by adding “or” at the end of paragraph (e) and by adding the following after paragraph (e):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a foreign national has committed transnational repression as an agent of or on behalf of a foreign state; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a foreign national has engaged in activities that undermine or are likely to undermine international peace, security or stability.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 4.4 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>4.4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within <Ins>24</Ins> months of the seizure or restraint of <Ins>private</Ins> property under an order made under paragraph 4(1)(b), the Minister must apply for forfeiture of the <Ins>private</Ins> property under section 4.2.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The <Ins>Minister</Ins> must dispose of the <Ins>private</Ins> property forfeited within 30 days of the forfeiture.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) do not apply in cases in respect of which legal proceedings are ongoing.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 5 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Order or regulation</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A copy of each order or regulation made under paragraph 4(1)(a) or (b) must be tabled in each House of Parliament within 15 days after it is made. It may be sent to the Clerk of the House if the House is not sitting.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>9.1</Label><Text>Paragraph 11b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable to a fine of not more than $100,000 or to imprisonment for a term of not more than three years, or to both.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1992, c. 17</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Special Economic Measures Act</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Text>Section 1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Global Sanctions <Ins>and Special Economic Measures</Ins> Act (Sergei Magnitsky <Ins>Law No. 2</Ins>)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>Section 2 of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>transnational repression</DefinedTermEn> means tactics used by a foreign state to intimidate, harass, surveil or threaten individuals or groups located outside the state borders or to physically harm such individuals or members of such groups, including elected officials, political dissidents, human rights defenders, exiled journalists, diaspora communities, civil society activists and refugees, for the purpose of silencing dissent and stifling activism. (<DefinedTermFr>répression transnationale</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section change="ins" type="amending"><Label>12.1</Label><Text>Section 3.1 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose of Act</MarginalNote><Label>3.1</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to enable the Government of Canada to take economic measures against certain persons in circumstances where an international organization of states or association of states of which Canada is a member calls on its members to do so, international peace, security or stability has been undermined or is likely to be undermined, gross and systematic human rights violations have been committed in a foreign state or acts of significant corruption involving a national of a foreign state have been committed.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(<Ins>1</Ins>)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>make any orders or regulations with respect to the restriction or prohibition of any of the activities referred to in subsection (2) that the Governor in Council considers necessary; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection change="ins" type="amending"><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(1.1)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>international peace, security or stability has been undermined or is likely to be undermined;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 4(1.1)(c) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>transnational repression or gross and systematic human rights violations have been committed in a foreign state; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection change="ins" type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 4(2) of the English version of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Restricted or prohibited activities</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Orders and regulations may be made under paragraph (1)(a) with respect to the restriction or prohibition of any of the following activities, whether carried out in or outside Canada:</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>Section 5.6 of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Forfeiture</MarginalNote><Label>5.6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within <Ins>24</Ins> months of the seizure or restraint of <Ins>private</Ins> property under an order made under paragraph 4(1)(b), the Minister must apply for forfeiture of the <Ins>private</Ins> property under section 5.4.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Disposal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The <Ins>Minister</Ins> must dispose of the <Ins>private</Ins> property forfeited within 30 days of the forfeiture.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsections (1) and (2) do not apply in cases in respect of which legal proceedings are ongoing.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>17</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>18</Label><Text>Subsection 7(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling in Parliament</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every order and regulation made under paragraph 4(1)(a) or (b) shall be laid before each House of Parliament by a member of the King’s Privy Council for Canada within five sitting days of that House after it is made.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>19</Label><Text>Paragraph 8(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction and is liable to a fine not exceeding one hundred thousand dollars or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding three years, or to both; or</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>20</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 10(1) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Evidence</MarginalNote><Label>10</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The original or a copy of a bill of lading, customs document, commercial invoice or other document is admissible in evidence in a prosecution under this <Ins>Part</Ins> in relation to any dealing with respect to goods, or services rendered in relation to these goods, where it appears from the document that</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="2" type="transitional"><TitleText>Terminology</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement of “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>” in other Acts</MarginalNote><Label>21</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>” is replaced by a reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Global Sanctions <Ins>and Special Economic Measures</Ins> Act (Sergei Magnitsky <Ins>Law No. 2</Ins>)</XRefExternal>” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph 13(3)‍(d) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Seized Property Management Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Act</XRefExternal>:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the definition <DefinedTermEn>sanctions evasion offence</DefinedTermEn> in subsection 2(1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>paragraph 7.1(1)(c),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>paragraph 11.‍11(1)‍(b.‍1),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>paragraph 39.27(3)(h),</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>section 39.28, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(vi)</Label><Text>paragraph 55(3)(h);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>paragraphs 35.1(1)(a) and (b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Immigration and Refugee Protection Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>paragraph 6(2)‍(d) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">International Interests in Mobile Equipment (aircraft equipment) Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>subsection 20(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Freezing Assets of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Justice for Victims of Corrupt Foreign Officials Act (Sergei Magnitsky Law)</XRefExternal>:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the long title,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the preamble, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>subsection 16(1);   and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>paragraphs 27(3.1)(a) and (b) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Online News Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other references — Acts</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, every reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>” in any provision of an Act of Parliament, other than a provision referred to in subsection (1), is to be read as a reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Global Sanctions <Ins>and Special Economic Measures</Ins> Act (Sergei Magnitsky <Ins>Law No. 2</Ins>)</XRefExternal>”.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><MarginalNote>Replacement in regulations</MarginalNote><Label>22</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>” is replaced by a reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Global Sanctions <Ins>and Special Economic Measures</Ins> Act (Sergei Magnitsky <Ins>Law No. 2</Ins>)</XRefExternal>” in the following provisions:</Text><Paragraph type="amending"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>paragraph (c) of the definition <Emphasis style="italic">listed person or entity</Emphasis> in subsection 1(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Proceeds of Crime (Money Laundering) and Terrorist Financing Suspicious Transaction Reporting Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Myanmar) Regulations</XRefExternal>:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 3.1(f), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 15(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>subsection 10(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Zimbabwe) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>subsection 10(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Iran) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Regulations Implementing the United Nations Resolutions and Imposing Special Economic Measures on Libya</XRefExternal>:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 2(2), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 24(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>subsection 6(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Syria) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(g)</Label><Text>paragraph 4(1)‍(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">General Export Permit No. 45 — Cryptography for the Development or Production of a Product</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(h)</Label><Text>paragraph 3(1)‍(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">General Export Permit No. 46 — Cryptography for Use by Certain Consignees</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Russia) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(j)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Ukraine) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(k)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (South Sudan) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(l)</Label><Text>paragraph 3(1)‍(c) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">General Export Permit No. 41 — Dual-use Goods and Technology to Certain Destinations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Venezuela) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(n)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Nicaragua) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(o)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Belarus) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(p)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (People’s Republic of China) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(q)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Haiti) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(r)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Sri Lanka) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(s)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Moldova) Regulations</XRefExternal>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(t)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Guatemala) Regulations</XRefExternal>:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 4(f), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(u)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Hamas Terrorist Attacks) Regulations</XRefExternal>:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 4(f), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2);</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(v)</Label><Text>in the <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Special Economic Measures (Sudan) Regulations</XRefExternal>:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 4(f), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2); and</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(w)</Label><Text>in the Special <XRefExternal reference-type="regulation">Economic Measures (Extremist Settler Violence) Regulations</XRefExternal>:</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>paragraph 4(f), and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>subsection 7(2).</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Other references — regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Unless the context requires otherwise, every reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Special Economic Measures Act</XRefExternal>” in any provision of a regulation, as defined in section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Statutory Instruments Act</XRefExternal>, made under an Act of Parliament, other than a provision referred to in subsection (1), is to be read as a reference to the “<XRefExternal reference-type="act">Global Sanctions <Ins>and Special Economic Measures</Ins> Act (Sergei Magnitsky <Ins>Law No. 2</Ins>)</XRefExternal>”. </Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1991, c. 11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Broadcasting Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>23</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>24</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section></Body></Bill>