<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002--><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="govt-public" xml:lang="en"><!--Authoring to Exchange Transform created with transform.acl--><Identification><BillNumber>C-28</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Aeronautics Act and other Acts</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Canadian Space Launch Act.</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Canadian Space Launch Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>21</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>MINISTER OF TRANSPORT</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2026-04-20">91262</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Recommendation><TitleText>RECOMMENDATION</TitleText><Provision format-ref="section"><Text>Her Excellency the Governor General recommends to the House of Commons the appropriation of public revenue under the circumstances, in the manner and for the purposes set out in a measure entitled “<Emphasis style="italic">An Act to amend the Aeronautics Act and other Acts</Emphasis>”.</Text></Provision></Recommendation><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> to establish a legislative framework for space launch and re-entry activities in Canada. It amends certain definitions to take into account new terms, such as launch vehicles and re-entry vehicles, and authorizes those terms to be defined by regulation. It also removes certain decisions related to launch and re-entry from review by the Transportation Appeal Tribunal of Canada. It expands the regulation-making powers, including in relation to launches and re-entries and the operation of launch and re-entry sites, as well as in relation to the application of certain international agreements and standards.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>This enactment also introduces new authorities related to liability and indemnification for launch and re-entry activities. It authorizes the Minister of Transport to indemnify owners and operators of launch or re-entry vehicles in certain circumstances, and when it is in the public interest, for their liability to third parties for loss or damage caused by their activities, and to require the owners and operators in certain circumstances to indemnify the Government of Canada for any liability to third parties for loss or damage caused by their activities. It establishes regulatory authority to create a distinct financial responsibility regime that includes the ability to grant exemptions or adjustments in specific cases. It provides for emergency authorities to allow the Minister to stop launch or re-entry activities for reasons of safety or security. Finally, it establishes a scheme related to the development of zoning regulations for certified launch and re-entry sites.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Carriage by Air Act</XRefExternal>, the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal> and the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Secure Air Travel Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes" list-item="no"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canadian Space Launch Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. A-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Aeronautics Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>The heading before section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation <Ins>and General Provisions</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText><Ins>Interpretation</Ins></TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The definitions <DefinitionRef>aircraft</DefinitionRef> and <DefinitionRef>airport</DefinitionRef> in subsection 3(1) of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>aircraft</DefinedTermEn> means any machine capable of deriving support in the atmosphere from reactions of the air, and includes a <Ins>launch vehicle and a re-entry vehicle</Ins>; (<DefinedTermFr>aéronef</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>airport</DefinedTermEn> means an aerodrome in respect of which a Canadian aviation document is in force, <Ins>other than a <DefinitionRef>certified launch site</DefinitionRef> or <DefinitionRef>certified re-entry site</DefinitionRef> as defined in subsection 5.4(1)</Ins>; (<DefinedTermFr>aéroport</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsection 3(3) of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after paragraph (d):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(e)</Label><Text>a permit or notice of determination issued by the Minister relating to the launch of a launch vehicle from within Canada;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(f)</Label><Text>a permit or notice of determination issued by the Minister relating to the re-entry into Canada of a re-entry vehicle;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(g)</Label><Text>a certificate issued by the Minister relating to the use of an aerodrome for the launch of a launch vehicle from within Canada; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(h)</Label><Text>a certificate issued by the Minister relating to the use of an aerodrome for the re-entry into Canada of a re-entry vehicle.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following before the heading “PART I”:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Heading change="ins" level="2"><TitleText><Ins>General Provisions</Ins></TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>3.1</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations defining “launch”, “launch vehicle” and “re-entry vehicle” for the purposes of this Act.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Transitional definitions</MarginalNote><Label>3.2</Label><Subsection change="ins"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>launch vehicle</DefinedTermEn> means</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>a rocket; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a vehicle, other than a rocket, that is designed to ascend to Earth orbit or beyond. (<DefinedTermFr>véhicule de lancement</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>re-entry vehicle</DefinedTermEn> means a vehicle that is designed to be returned by its operator, substantially intact, from Earth orbit or beyond to Earth. (<DefinedTermFr>véhicule de rentrée atmosphérique</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Repeal</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>This section is repealed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Coming into force</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Subsection (2) comes into force on the day on which a regulation made under section 3.1 that defines both “launch vehicle” and “re-entry vehicle” comes into force.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 4.32:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Indemnification of owners and operators</MarginalNote><Label>4.33</Label><Text>Subject to any regulations made under paragraph 5(b.3), the Minister may, if of the opinion that it is in the public interest to do so, indemnify the owner or operator, or both, of a launch vehicle or re-entry vehicle against their liability to third parties for loss or damage caused by a launch of the launch vehicle or re-entry of the re-entry vehicle that is carried out under this Act, on any terms and conditions that the Minister considers to be in the public interest.</Text></Section><Section change="ins"><MarginalNote>Indemnification of Government of Canada</MarginalNote><Label>4.34</Label><Text>The Minister may require, in accordance with any regulations made under paragraph 5(b.4), the owner or operator, or both, of a launch vehicle or re-entry vehicle to indemnify the Government of Canada against any liability to third parties for loss or damage — including in the event of a claim arising out of the Convention on International Liability for Damage Caused by Space Objects, which entered into force on September 1, 1972, as amended from time to time — that is caused by a launch of the launch vehicle or re-entry of the re-entry vehicle that is carried out under this Act.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Section 4.76 of the Act is amended by striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (b), by adding “and” at the end of paragraph (c) and by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>the stopping of the launch of a launch vehicle or the re-entry of a re-entry vehicle or the stopping of any activity related to a launch or re-entry.</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 4.9 of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (e):</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e.1)</Label><Text>the issuance by the Minister of certificates relating to the use of aerodromes for the launch of launch vehicles from within Canada or the re-entry into Canada of re-entry vehicles, and the renewal, amendment, suspension, transfer or cancellation of those certificates by the Minister;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Section 4.9 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (h):</Text><AmendedText change="ins" include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label><Ins>(h.1)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>the issuance by the Minister of permits or notices of determination relating to the launch of launch vehicles from within Canada or the re-entry into Canada of re-entry vehicles, and the renewal, amendment, suspension, transfer or cancellation of those permits or notices by the Minister;</Ins></Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 4.9 of the Act is amended striking out “and” at the end of paragraph (v) and by replacing paragraph (w) by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(w)</Label><Text>the application of <Ins>any international convention, agreement or arrangement to which Canada is a party, including</Ins> the Convention on International Civil Aviation signed at Chicago, 7 December 1944, as amended from time to time; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label><Ins>(x)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>the application of international standards.</Ins></Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>8</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>requiring owners and operators of aircraft, <Ins>other than launch vehicles and re-entry vehicles</Ins>, to subscribe for and carry liability insurance and specifying the minimum amount of that insurance, if the owners and operators are not required by regulations made by the Canadian Transportation Agency to subscribe for and carry liability insurance;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.1)</Label><Text>respecting the financial responsibility of operators of launch vehicles or re-entry vehicles for liability to third parties for loss or damage caused by a launch or re-entry that is carried out under this Act and the minimum amount of an operator’s financial responsibility;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.2)</Label><Text>defining “financial responsibility” for the purposes of paragraph (b.1) and subsection 5.9(2.2);</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.3)</Label><Text>respecting the indemnification of owners and operators under section 4.33;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.4)</Label><Text>respecting the indemnification of the Government of Canada under section 4.34; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>9</Label><Text>Section 5.3 of the Act and the heading after it are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Relationship to <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Explosives Act</XRefExternal></MarginalNote><Label>5.3</Label><Text>Regulations made under this Part respecting the use and operation of <Ins>launch vehicles or re-entry vehicles</Ins> are in addition to and not in derogation of the provisions of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Explosives Act</XRefExternal> and regulations made <Ins>under it</Ins> and, <Ins>if</Ins> there is any conflict between any regulation respecting <Ins>launch vehicles</Ins> or <Ins>re-entry vehicles</Ins> made under this Part and any regulation made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Explosives Act</XRefExternal>, the regulation made under the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Explosives Act</XRefExternal> prevails.</Text></Section><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Airport, <Ins>Certified Launch Site and Certified Re-entry Site</Ins> Zoning</TitleText></Heading></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>10</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 5.4(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following in alphabetical order:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>certified launch site</DefinedTermEn> means an aerodrome in respect of which there is in force a certificate issued by the Minister under this Part authorizing the use of the aerodrome for the launch of a launch vehicle from within Canada; (<DefinedTermFr>zone de lancement certifiée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>certified re-entry site</DefinedTermEn> means an aerodrome in respect of which there is in force a certificate issued by the Minister under this Part authorizing the use of the aerodrome for the re-entry into Canada of a re-entry vehicle; (<DefinedTermFr>zone de rentrée atmosphérique certifiée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated launch site</DefinedTermEn> means any land that is not part of an existing certified launch site, is declared by order of the Governor in Council to be required for use as a certified launch site and meets one of the following requirements:</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the title to the land is vested in or the land otherwise belongs to His Majesty in right of Canada, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a notice of intention to expropriate the land under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal> has been registered; (<DefinedTermFr>zone de lancement désignée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition change="ins"><Text><DefinedTermEn>designated re-entry site</DefinedTermEn> means any land that is not part of an existing certified re-entry site, is declared by order of the Governor in Council to be required for use as a certified re-entry site and meets one of the following requirements:</Text><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the title to the land is vested in or the land otherwise belongs to His Majesty in right of Canada, or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>a notice of intention to expropriate the land under section 5 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Expropriation Act</XRefExternal> has been registered; (<DefinedTermFr>zone de rentrée atmosphérique désignée</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Paragraph 5.4(2)(b) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.1)</Label><Text>preventing lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of a designated launch site from being used or developed in a manner that is, in the opinion of the Minister, incompatible with the operation of a certified launch site;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a.2)</Label><Text>preventing lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of a designated re-entry site from being used or developed in a manner that is, in the opinion of the Minister, incompatible with the operation of a certified re-entry site;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>preventing lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of an airport or airport site from being used or developed in a manner that is, in the opinion of the Minister, incompatible with the safe operation of an airport or <Ins>of</Ins> aircraft <Ins>other than launch vehicles or re-entry vehicles</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label><Ins>(b.1)</Ins></Label><Text><Ins>preventing lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of a certified launch site or designated launch site from being used or developed in a manner that is, in the opinion of the Minister, incompatible with the safe operation of a certified launch site or a launch vehicle;</Ins></Text></Paragraph><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.2)</Label><Text>preventing lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of a certified re-entry site or designated re-entry site from being used or developed in a manner that is, in the opinion of the Minister, incompatible with the safe operation of a certified re-entry site or a re-entry vehicle; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Section 5.4 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (3):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Conditions precedent — paragraph (2)(a.1)</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall not make a zoning regulation under paragraph (2)(a.1) unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Minister, after making a reasonable attempt to do so, has been unable to reach an agreement with the government of the province in which the lands to which the zoning regulation applies are situated providing for the use or development of the lands in a manner that is compatible with the operation of a certified launch site; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the opinion of the Minister, it is necessary to immediately prevent the use or development of the lands to which the zoning regulation applies in a manner that is incompatible with the operation of a certified launch site.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Conditions precedent — paragraph (2)(a.2)</MarginalNote><Label>(3.2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council shall not make a zoning regulation under paragraph (2)(a.2) unless</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the Minister, after making a reasonable attempt to do so, has been unable to reach an agreement with the government of the province in which the lands to which the zoning regulation applies are situated providing for the use or development of the lands in a manner that is compatible with the operation of a certified re-entry site; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>in the opinion of the Minister, it is necessary to immediately prevent the use or development of the lands to which the zoning regulation applies in a manner that is incompatible with the operation of a certified re-entry site.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>11</Label><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 5.81(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Section><MarginalNote>Agreements with a provincial authority — airports and airport sites</MarginalNote><Label>5.81</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement with a provincial authority to authorize the provincial authority to regulate, in the same manner and to the same extent as it may regulate the use of lands within its jurisdiction, the use of lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of an airport or airport site that are not the subject of regulations made <Ins>under</Ins> subsection 5.4(2), for the purpose of ensuring that that use is not incompatible with the safe operation of an airport or <Ins>of</Ins> aircraft <Ins>other than launch vehicles or re-entry vehicles</Ins>.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Agreements with a provincial authority — launch sites</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement with a provincial authority to authorize the provincial authority to regulate, in the same manner and to the same extent as it may regulate the use of lands within its jurisdiction, the use of lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of a certified launch site or designated launch site that are not the subject of regulations made under subsection 5.4(2), for the purpose of ensuring that that use is not incompatible with the safe operation of a certified launch site or a launch vehicle.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Agreements with a provincial authority — re-entry sites</MarginalNote><Label>(1.2)</Label><Text>The Minister may enter into an agreement with a provincial authority to authorize the provincial authority to regulate, in the same manner and to the same extent as it may regulate the use of lands within its jurisdiction, the use of lands adjacent to or in the vicinity of a certified re-entry site or designated re-entry site that are not the subject of regulations made under subsection 5.4(2), for the purpose of ensuring that that use is not incompatible with the safe operation of a certified re-entry site or a re-entry vehicle.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 5.81(2) and (3) of the English version of the Act are replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Saving</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Subsections 5.4(3) to (5) and sections 5.5 to 5.7 <Ins>do</Ins> not apply in respect of lands that are the subject of an agreement made under <Ins>any of subsections</Ins> (1) <Ins>to (1.2)</Ins>, during the period in which the agreement remains in effect.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contravention</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>Every person who contravenes a regulation or other measure established by a provincial authority <Ins>under</Ins> an agreement referred to in <Ins>any of subsections</Ins> (1) to <Ins>(1.2)</Ins> is guilty of an offence punishable on summary conviction.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>12</Label><Text>Subsection 5.9(2) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exemption by Minister</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister or an officer of the Department of Transport authorized by the Minister for the purpose of this subsection may, on any terms and conditions that the Minister or officer, as the case may be, considers necessary, exempt any person, aeronautical product, aerodrome, facility or service, or any class of persons, aeronautical products, aerodromes, facilities or services, from the application of any regulation, order or security measure made under this Part — <Ins>other than a regulation made under paragraph 5(b.1)</Ins> — if the exemption, in the opinion of the Minister or officer, as the case may be, is in the public interest and is not likely to adversely affect aviation safety or security.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Exemption by Minister — regulation under paragraph 5(b.1)</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>The Minister or an officer of the Department of Transport authorized by the Minister for the purpose of this subsection may, on any terms and conditions that the Minister or the officer, as the case may be, considers to be in the public interest, exempt any person or any class of persons from the application of any regulation made under paragraph 5(b.1) if the exemption, in the opinion of the Minister or the officer, as the case may be, is in the public interest.</Text></Subsection><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Adjustment of amount of financial responsibility</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>The Minister or an officer of the Department of Transport authorized by the Minister for the purpose of this subsection may, on any terms and conditions that the Minister or officer, as the case may be, considers to be in the public interest, adjust downward the minimum amount of the financial responsibility of a person who is subject to a regulation made under paragraph 5(b.1), if the adjustment, in the opinion of the Minister or officer, as the case may be, is in the public interest.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>13</Label><Text>Paragraph 6.2(1)(d) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>an exemption made under subsection 5.9(2) <Ins>or (2.1)</Ins>; and</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-26</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Carriage by Air Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>14</Label><Text>Section 1.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Carriage by Air Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Clarification — aircraft</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a reference to “aircraft” in this Act does not include a <DefinitionRef>launch vehicle</DefinitionRef> or <DefinitionRef>re-entry vehicle</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 10</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>15</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>air service</DefinitionRef> in subsection 55(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Transportation Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>air service</DefinedTermEn> means a service, provided by means of an aircraft <Ins>other than a <DefinitionRef>launch vehicle</DefinitionRef> or <DefinitionRef>re-entry vehicle</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal></Ins>, that is publicly available for the transportation of passengers or goods, or both; (<DefinedTermFr>service aérien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2015, c. 20, s. 11</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Secure Air Travel Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>16</Label><Text>The definition <DefinitionRef>air carrier</DefinitionRef> in section 3 of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Secure Air Travel Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText include-in-TableOfProvisions="no"><SectionPiece><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>air carrier</DefinedTermEn> has the same meaning as in subsection 3(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Aeronautics Act</XRefExternal> <Ins>except that, for the purposes of this Act, the reference to “aircraft” in the definition <DefinitionRef>commercial air service</DefinitionRef> in that subsection is to be read as excluding <DefinitionRef>launch vehicles</DefinitionRef> and <DefinitionRef>re-entry vehicles</DefinitionRef> within the meaning of that Act</Ins>. (<DefinedTermFr>transporteur aérien</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>