<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2026-04-02 11:47:15"><Identification><BillNumber>S-247</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to establish a national framework on food <Keep>allergy</Keep></LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">National Framework on Food Allergy Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>National Framework on Food Allergy Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>5</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator CARDOZO</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512527</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment provides for the development of a national framework on food allergy.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas food allergy is a serious and growing public health concern affecting over 3 million Canadians, <Keep>including</Keep> 600,000 children, with nearly 25,000 infants diagnosed each year;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas food allergy imposes a significant daily burden upon those affected, requiring them to navigate safe food options and be prepared, if necessary, to treat reactions;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas access to allergists is limited, particularly in rural and remote areas, thus impacting patients’ ability to secure timely diagnoses and care to safely manage food allergy;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas there has been a fundamental shift in primary prevention guidance that is now focused on early introduction and ongoing ingestion of food <Keep>allergens</Keep> in infants, offering a potential 80% reduction in the incidence of food allergy;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas clinically validated, disease-modifying treatment approaches exist and demonstrate greater <Keep>effectiveness</Keep> when initiated in infancy and early childhood but remain limited by inadequate awareness, support and access;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas prompt use of epinephrine in pre-hospital settings has the highest impact on anaphylaxis management but is significantly underutilized due to lack of access to a device and lack of understanding and confidence in when to use it;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas individuals with food allergy rely on accurate ingredient information to navigate safe food choices but are unable to consistently access this <Keep>information</Keep>;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">National Framework on Food Allergy Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definition</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>In this Act, <DefinedTermEn>Indigenous governing body</DefinedTermEn> means a council, government or other entity that is authorized to act on behalf of an Indigenous group, community or people that holds rights recognized and affirmed by section 35 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act" reference-level="other-jurisdiction">Constitution Act, 1982</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>National Framework</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Development</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Health must, in consultation with provincial and territorial government representatives <Keep>responsible</Keep> for health and with Indigenous governing bodies, relevant healthcare professionals, patient groups and other relevant stakeholders, develop a national framework on food allergy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Contents</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The framework must identify measures to reduce the incidence and risk of food allergy, including measures to</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>ensure that those affected by food allergy can receive timely diagnoses and care;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>integrate evidence-based practices for preventing food allergy, including early allergen introduction, <Keep>into</Keep> national public health initiatives;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>ensure reliable access to essential medications — including epinephrine devices — and treatments for food allergy;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>improve access to accurate ingredient information to enable safe food choices;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>improve public awareness of food allergy and <Keep>anaphylaxis</Keep>, as well as society’s critical role in ensuring a safer, more inclusive environment for those at risk; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>support research and innovation in the prevention and treatment of food allergy.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Advisory Board</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Appointment of members</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>The Minister of Health must establish an advisory board and appoint no more than 15 members to hold <Keep>office</Keep> during pleasure for a term not exceeding three years. The term may be renewed for one or more further terms.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Chairperson</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must appoint one of the members as chair of the advisory board.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Role of advisory board</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The board is to advise the Minister on any matter <Keep>related</Keep> to food allergy.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Representation</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Minister may appoint to the advisory board any person with relevant knowledge or expertise, including</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text> federal, provincial and territorial government <Keep>representatives</Keep> responsible for public health;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>representatives from Indigenous governing bodies;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>representatives from food allergy advocacy groups and other related advocacy groups;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>health care professionals; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>people living with food allergy and their caregivers.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No remuneration</MarginalNote><Label>(5)</Label><Text>No member of the advisory board is to receive remuneration for the performance of their duties.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Meetings</MarginalNote><Label>(6)</Label><Text>Advisory board meetings must be held at least twice annually, at times and places to be determined by the chair.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Reports to Parliament</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Tabling of framework</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within 18 months after the day on which this Act comes into force, the Minister of Health must prepare a report setting out the national framework and cause it to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the Department of Health website within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Report</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Within three years after the day on which the <Keep>report</Keep> referred to in section 5 is tabled in both Houses of Parliament, the Minister of Health must prepare a report on the effectiveness of the national framework in reducing the incidence and risk of food allergy and the Minister’s conclusions and recommendations regarding the framework.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Tabling of report</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Minister must cause the report to be tabled in each House of Parliament on any of the first 15 days on which that House is sitting after the report is completed.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Publication</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The Minister must publish the report on the Department of Health website within 10 days after the day on which it is tabled in Parliament.</Text></Subsection></Section></Body></Bill>