<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2025-09-15 17:53:39"><Identification><BillNumber>C-231</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Youth Criminal Justice Act</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>An Act to amend the Youth Criminal Justice Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>1</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Justice and Human Rights as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on June 1, 2026</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Berthold</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-09-15">451084</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> in order to</Text><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>clarify the measures governing problematic substance use treatment programs for young persons;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(b)</Label><Text>enable, in some cases, the youth justice court that finds a young person guilty of an offence to delay sentencing to enable the young person to participate in a problematic substance use treatment program or any other treatment program;</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(c)</Label><Text>enable the youth justice court to include in certain orders the condition of attending a problematic substance use treatment program or any other treatment program; and</Text></Provision><Provision first-line-indent="1" subsequent-line-indent="1"><Label>(d)</Label><Text>provide that the youth justice court may include in an order for conditional supervision a condition that the young person attend a problematic substance use treatment program or any other treatment program.</Text></Provision></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>2002, c. 1</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Youth Criminal Justice Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>1</Label><Text>Section 6 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Problematic substance use treatment program</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), if the young person <Ins>is</Ins> alleged <Ins>to have committed an</Ins> offence <Ins>under</Ins> subsection <Ins>4</Ins>(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> or subsection <Ins>8</Ins>(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cannabis Act</XRefExternal>, the police officer shall consider whether it would be <Ins>sufficient</Ins> to refer the young person, with the young person’s consent, to a <Ins>problematic substance use</Ins> treatment program.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text><Ins>Section</Ins> 10 of the Act is <Ins>amended</Ins> by <Ins>adding</Ins> the following <Ins>after subsection (3)</Ins>:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Treatment program</MarginalNote><Label>(3.1)</Label><Text>An extrajudicial sanction may include requiring a young person to attend a problematic substance use treatment program or any other treatment program.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>3.1</Label><Text>The Act is amended by adding the following after section 41:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Treatment program</MarginalNote><Label>41.1</Label><Text>If a youth justice court finds a young person guilty of any offence, the court may, before imposing a specific sentence, while taking into account the principles set out in subparagraphs 3(1)(b)(iv) and (v) and the purpose and principles set out in section 38 and with the consent of the Attorney General and the young person, delay sentencing to enable the young person to attend a problematic substance use treatment program or any other treatment program.</Text></Section></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 42(1) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Section><MarginalNote>Considerations as to youth sentence</MarginalNote><Label>42</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>A youth justice court shall, before imposing a youth sentence, consider any recommendations submitted under section 41, any pre-sentence report, any representations made by the parties to the proceedings or their counsel or agents and by the parents of the young person, any participation by the young person in a program referred to in <Ins>section 41.1</Ins>, and any other relevant information before the court.</Text></Subsection></Section></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text><Ins>Paragraph</Ins> 42(2)(m) of the Act <Ins>is</Ins> replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(m)</Label><Text>subject to subsection (3) (agreement of provincial director) and section 54, order the young person to attend a non-residential program — including <Ins>a problematic substance use</Ins> treatment program <Ins>or any other treatment program</Ins> — approved by the provincial director, at the times and on the terms that the court may fix, for a maximum of two hundred and forty hours, over a period not exceeding six months;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Subsection 55(2) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (e):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(e.1)</Label><Text>attend a <Ins>problematic substance use</Ins> treatment program <Ins>or any other treatment program</Ins>;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>5.1</Label><Text>Subsection 105(3) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (c):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph><Label>(c.1)</Label><Text>attend a problematic substance use treatment program or any other treatment program;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Coordinating Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><MarginalNote>Bill C-16</MarginalNote><Label>5.2</Label><Text>If Bill C-16, introduced in the 1st session of the 45th Parliament and entitled the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Protecting Victims Act</XRefExternal>, receives royal assent, then on the first day on which both section 123 of that Act and section 1 of this Act are in force, section 6.1 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Youth Criminal Justice Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (1):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Problematic substance use treatment program</MarginalNote><Label>(1.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), if the young person is alleged to have committed an offence under subsection 4(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> or subsection 8(1) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Cannabis Act</XRefExternal>, the prosecutor shall consider whether it would be sufficient to refer the young person, with the young person’s consent, to a problematic substance use treatment program.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><MarginalNote>30th day after royal assent</MarginalNote><Label>5.3</Label><Text>This Act, other than section 5.2, comes into force on the 30th day after the day on which it receives royal assent.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>