<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2025-08-11 11:10:17"><Identification><BillNumber>C-222</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Employment Insurance Act and the Canada Labour Code (death of a child)</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Relieving Grieving Parents of an Administrative Burden Act (Evan's Law)</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="report-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>4</MM><DD>22</DD></Date><StageText>Reprinted as amended by the Standing Committee on Human Resources, Skills and Social Development and the Status of Persons with Disabilities as a working copy for the use of the House of Commons at Report Stage and as reported to the House on April 22, 2026</StageText></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Beech</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2025-08-11">451105</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> to provide that a person to whom employment insurance benefits are payable to care for a newborn child or a child placed with them for the purpose of adoption remains eligible to receive those benefits even if the child dies during the benefit period. It also amends the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> to extend the period of bereavement leave to which an employee is entitled in the event of the death of a child of the employee or of their spouse or <Keep>common-law</Keep> partner. </Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent <Keep>of the</Keep> Senate and House of Commons of Canada, <Keep>enacts</Keep> as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Relieving Grieving Parents of an Administrative Burden Act (Evan's Law)</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 23</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Employment Insurance Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Section 23 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Employment Insurance Act</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Benefits still payable — death of child</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), paragraphs 12(3)(b) and (4)(b) and subsection 12(4.01), if the child or children referred to in that subsection (1) die during the period referred to in subsection (2), the claimant is deemed to care for the child or children until that period expires.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No report or new claim required</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, the claimant referred to in subsection (2.1) is not required to make a new claim for benefits or file a report to prove their eligibility to receive or continue to receive benefits.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>Subsection (2.1) does not apply if the child or children die as the result of the commission of an offence and the claimant is convicted of the offence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Section 152.05 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Benefits still payable — death of child</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), paragraphs 152.14(1)(b) and (2)(b) and subsection 152.14(4), if the child or children referred to in that subsection (1) die during the period referred to in subsection (2), the self-employed person is deemed to care for the child or children until that period expires.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>No report or new claim required</MarginalNote><Label>(2.2)</Label><Text>Despite any other provision of this Act, the self-<Keep>employed</Keep> person referred to in subsection (2.1) is not required to make a new claim for benefits or file a report to prove their eligibility to receive or continue to receive benefits.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Exception</MarginalNote><Label>(2.3)</Label><Text>Subsection (2.1) does not apply if the child or children die as the result of the commission of an offence and the self-employed person is convicted of the offence.</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. L-2</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText>Canada Labour Code</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><TitleText>Amendments to the Act</TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>[<Emphasis style="italic">Deleted</Emphasis>]</Text></Section><Section type="amending" change="ins"><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Subsection 210(1.01) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Death of child</MarginalNote><Label>(1.01)</Label><Text>Subject to subsection (1.011), every employee is entitled to and shall be granted, in the event of the death of a child of the employee or the death of a child of their spouse or common-law partner, a leave of absence from employment of up to 10 weeks that may be taken during the period that begins on the day on which the death occurs and ends 12 weeks after the latest of the days on which any funeral, burial or memorial service of the child occurs.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Death of child — leave under section 206</MarginalNote><Label>(1.011)</Label><Text>Every employee is entitled to and shall be granted, in the event of the death of a child of the employee that occurs while the employee is on, or is entitled to be on, leave under section 206 in respect of that child, a leave of absence from employment of up to 10 weeks that may be taken during the period that begins on the day on which the death occurs and ends on the later of</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>12 weeks after the latest of the days on which any funeral, burial or memorial service of the child occurs; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>12 weeks after the end of the leave under section 206.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection><Subsection change="ins" type="amending"><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The portion of subsection 210(1.02) of the Act before paragraph (a) is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><Subsection><MarginalNote>Definition of <DefinedTermEn>child</DefinedTermEn></MarginalNote><Label>(1.02)</Label><Text>In subsections (1.01) and (1.011), <DefinitionRef>child</DefinitionRef> means</Text></Subsection></AmendedText></Subsection></Section><Heading level="2" change="ins"><TitleText>Transitional Provisions</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><MarginalNote><XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> — section 210</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Section 210 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal>, as amended by section 6, applies to an employee if, on the day on which section 6 comes into force,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the period during which the employee is entitled to take leave under subsection 210(1.01) of that Act, as it read immediately before section 6 comes into force, has not ended; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the employee is on, or entitled to be on, leave under section 206 of that Act.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Periods of leave</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>For the purposes of subsection (1), an employee who has taken two periods of leave under subsection 210(1.2) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Canada Labour Code</XRefExternal> before the day on which section 6 comes into force may, despite that subsection, take one additional period of leave.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1" change="ins"><TitleText>Coming into Force</TitleText></Heading><Section change="ins" type="amending"><MarginalNote>First Sunday after six months or order in council</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Text>This Act comes into force on the first Sunday after the day that is six months after the day on which this Act receives royal assent or on an earlier day to be fixed by order of the Governor in Council.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>