<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2026-03-17 12:48:05"><Identification><BillNumber>C-277</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to provide for the regulation of the online use of deepfakes and for related transparency measures</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial" /><RunningHead>Regulating the Online Use of Deepfakes Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>6</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Coteau</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2026-03-17">451077</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment enacts the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Regulating the Online Use of Deepfakes Act</XRefExternal> to regulate the online use and dissemination of deepfakes, to increase transparency and to protect individuals and their interests from significant harm. It also establishes an administrative monetary penalties scheme to promote compliance with the Act.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas advances in digital technologies, including artificial intelligence, have enabled the creation of highly realistic deepfake images, audio and video that can falsely represent an individual without their knowledge or consent;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas such deepfakes are increasingly being used for fraud, identity theft, harassment, intimidation and other forms of abuse that cause serious emotional, reputational and financial harm to individuals and their families;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the unauthorized use or manipulation of an individual’s identifiable characteristics, including their appearance or voice, to create false representations can undermine personal autonomy, dignity and privacy, as well as trust in authentic communication and information;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas existing legal frameworks do not provide adequate protection against the harms that deepfakes may cause;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas Parliament believes it is in the public interest to provide better protections to individuals against those harms by regulating the online use and dissemination of deepfakes;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision language-align="yes"><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Regulating the Online Use of Deepfakes Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Interpretation</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Definitions</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>The following definitions apply in this Act.</Text><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>deepfake</DefinedTermEn> means a photographic, video or audio recording of an individual that, in a manner that is intended to make the recording appear or sound authentic,</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>is edited through the use of an artificial intelligence system to replace the individual’s appearance or voice; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>is created through the use of an artificial intelligence system and uses an individual’s identifiable characteristics  — such as their appearance or voice. (<DefinedTermFr>hypertrucage</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Paragraph></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>Minister</DefinedTermEn> means the Minister of Industry. (<DefinedTermFr>ministre</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>operator</DefinedTermEn> means the owner or operator of an online undertaking, within the meaning of section 2 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Broadcasting Act</XRefExternal>, or of a platform, such as an online service or application, that connects to the Internet, including a social media service. (<DefinedTermFr>exploitant</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>significant harm</DefinedTermEn> includes psychological harm, such as humiliation and damage to reputation or relationships, as well as economic losses, such as loss of business, professional or employment opportunities, and identity theft. (<DefinedTermFr>préjudice grave</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition><Definition><Text><DefinedTermEn>social media service</DefinedTermEn> means a website or application that is accessible in Canada, the primary purpose of which is to facilitate interprovincial or international online communication among users of the website or application by enabling them to access and share content. (<DefinedTermFr>service de média social</DefinedTermFr>)</Text></Definition></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Purpose</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Purpose</MarginalNote><Label>3</Label><Text>The purpose of this Act is to protect individuals and their interests from the significant harm that may be caused by deepfakes by regulating their online use and dissemination, including by increasing transparency with respect to their use.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Duties of Operators</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Duty to establish process</MarginalNote><Label>4</Label><Text>Every operator must establish a process to identify any deepfake that is shared via its products or services, including reporting mechanisms for users.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duty of transparency</MarginalNote><Label>5</Label><Text>Every operator must take reasonable steps in the design and operation of its products and services to ensure that any deepfake that is shared via its products or services is clearly identified as such.</Text></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duty of care</MarginalNote><Label>6</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every operator must take reasonable steps in the design and operation of its products and services to prevent any deepfake that may cause significant harm to an individual or to their interests from being shared via its products or services.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Removal of content</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>Every operator must remove from its products and services a deepfake referred to in subsection (1) as soon as feasible after it has been identified.</Text></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Duty to keep records</MarginalNote><Label>7</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every operator must keep all records, including information and data, that are necessary to determine whether the operator is complying with its duties under this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting the records to be kept and maintained by an operator.</Text></Subsection></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Administrative Monetary Penalties</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Violations</MarginalNote><Label>8</Label><Subsection><Label>(1)</Label><Text>Every operator who is found under the regulations to have committed a violation is liable to the administrative monetary penalty established by the regulations.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Party to violation</MarginalNote><Label>(2)</Label><Text>If an operator commits a violation, any director or officer of the operator that directed, authorized, assented to, acquiesced in or participated in the commission of the violation is a party to the violation and is liable to a penalty of an amount to be determined in accordance with the regulations, whether or not the operator has been proceeded against in accordance with this Act.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Purpose of penalty</MarginalNote><Label>(3)</Label><Text>The purpose of an administrative monetary penalty is to promote compliance with this Act and not to punish.</Text></Subsection><Subsection><MarginalNote>Regulations</MarginalNote><Label>(4)</Label><Text>The Governor in Council may make regulations respecting an administrative monetary penalties scheme, including regulations</Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>designating the provisions of this Act or of the regulations the contravention of which constitutes a violation, including those provisions the contravention of which, if continued on more than one day, constitutes a separate violation in respect of each day during which the violation is continued;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>respecting the proceedings in respect of a violation, including in relation to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>commencing the proceedings,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>maintaining the confidentiality of information in the proceedings,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the defences that may be available in respect of a violation, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the circumstances in which the proceedings may be brought to an end;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(c)</Label><Text>respecting the administrative monetary penalties that may be imposed for a violation, including in relation to</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>the amount, or range of amounts, of the administrative monetary penalties that may be imposed for a violation,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>the factors to be taken into account in imposing an administrative monetary penalty,</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iii)</Label><Text>the payment of administrative monetary penalties, and</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(iv)</Label><Text>the recovery, as a debt, of unpaid administrative monetary penalties;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(d)</Label><Text>respecting reviews or appeals of findings that a violation has been committed and of the imposition of administrative monetary penalties;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(e)</Label><Text>respecting compliance agreements; and</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(f)</Label><Text>respecting the persons or classes of persons who may exercise any power, or perform any duty or function, in relation to the scheme, including the designation of such persons or classes of persons by the Minister.</Text></Paragraph></Subsection></Section><Section><MarginalNote>Violations not offences</MarginalNote><Label>9</Label><Text>For greater certainty, a violation is not an offence and, accordingly, section 126 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> does not apply in respect of a violation.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>