<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="commons" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2026-03-13 14:11:06"><Identification><BillNumber>C-289</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act to amend the Controlled Drugs and Substances Act and to make a related amendment to the Criminal Code</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Stopping Supply to Save Lives Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Stopping Supply to Save Lives Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-house"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>6</MM><DD>17</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor><Emphasis style="smallcaps">Mr. Au</Emphasis></BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="2026-03-13">451143</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>This enactment amends the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> to increase penalties for offenders who traffic, possess for the purpose of trafficking, import, export or produce certain amounts of synthetic opioids.</Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>It also amends that Act to add as aggravating factors for sentencing purposes in relation to offences respecting synthetic opioids the fact that the offence was committed in proximity to certain facilities or that the offence involved a certain amount of the substance. </Text></Provision><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>Finally, it amends the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> to provide that certain offenders who traffic, possess for the purpose of trafficking, import, export or produce certain amounts of synthetic opioids are ineligible for parole for 25 years.</Text></Provision></Summary><Enacts><Provision format-ref="indent-0-0" language-align="yes"><Text>His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Stopping Supply to Save Lives Act</XRefExternal>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>1996, c. 19</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>2</Label><Text>Paragraph 5(3)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal> is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the subject matter of the offence is a synthetic opioid included in Schedule I,</Text><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(i)</Label><Text>if the amount of the substance is more than <Keep>40 mg</Keep>, is guilty of an indictable offence and shall be sentenced to imprisonment for life, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph change="ins"><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>if the amount of the substance is equal to or greater than 20 mg but is not more than 40 mg, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life and to a minimum punishment of imprisonment for a term of 15 years;</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Ins>a.1</Ins>)</Label><Text>if the subject matter of the offence is a substance included in Schedule I or II, <Ins>other than a substance described in paragraph (a) in an amount of 20 mg or more</Ins>, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>3</Label><Text>Paragraph 6(3)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the subject matter of the offence is a synthetic opioid included in Schedule I in an amount of more than <Keep>40 mg</Keep>, is guilty of an indictable offence and shall be sentenced to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Ins>a.1</Ins>)</Label><Text>if the subject matter of the offence is a substance included in Schedule I or II, <Ins>other than a substance described in paragraph (a) in an amount of more than 40 mg</Ins>, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>4</Label><Text>Paragraph 7(2)(a) of the Act is replaced by the following:</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(a)</Label><Text>if the subject matter of the offence is a synthetic opioid included in Schedule I in an amount of more than <Keep>40 mg</Keep>, is guilty of an indictable offence and shall be sentenced to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(<Ins>a.1</Ins>)</Label><Text>if the subject matter of the offence is a substance included in Schedule I or II, <Ins>other than a substance described in paragraph (a) in an amount of more than 40 mg</Ins>, is guilty of an indictable offence and liable to imprisonment for life;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>5</Label><Text>Section 10 of the Act is amended by adding the following after subsection (2):</Text><AmendedText><Subsection change="ins"><MarginalNote>Aggravating factors — certain substances</MarginalNote><Label>(2.1)</Label><Text>If a person is convicted of a designated substance offence in respect of a substance that is a synthetic opioid included in Schedule I, the court imposing the sentence on the person shall consider as an aggravating factor the fact that </Text><Paragraph><Label>(a)</Label><Text>the person committed the offence within 300 metres of a substance use treatment centre, school, child care facility or any other location used for the protection of vulnerable persons that is designated by the regulations; or</Text></Paragraph><Paragraph><Label>(b)</Label><Text>the amount of the substance in respect of which the offence was committed was</Text><Subparagraph><Label>(i)</Label><Text>in the case of a substance listed in item 16 of Schedule I, 2 mg or more, or</Text></Subparagraph><Subparagraph><Label>(ii)</Label><Text>in the case of any other substance, equal to or more than the amount that could be reasonably expected to cause death if consumed by a person.</Text></Subparagraph></Paragraph></Subsection></AmendedText></Section><Section type="amending"><Label>6</Label><Text>Subsection 55(1) of the Act is amended by adding the following after paragraph (w):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(w.1)</Label><Text>designating any location for the purposes of paragraph 10(2.1)(a);</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Related Amendment</TitleText></Heading><Heading level="2"><MarginalNote><HistoricalNote>R.S., c. C-46</HistoricalNote></MarginalNote><TitleText><XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal></TitleText></Heading><Section type="amending"><Label>7</Label><Text>Section 745 of the <XRefExternal reference-type="act">Criminal Code</XRefExternal> is amended by adding the following after paragraph (b.1):</Text><AmendedText><SectionPiece><Paragraph change="ins"><Label>(b.2)</Label><Text>in respect of a person who has been convicted of an offence under subparagraph 5(3)(a)(i) or paragraph 6(3)(a) or 7(2)(a) of the <XRefExternal reference-level="federal" reference-type="act">Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</XRefExternal>, that the person be sentenced to imprisonment for life without eligibility for parole until the person has served twenty-five years of the sentence;</Text></Paragraph></SectionPiece></AmendedText></Section></Body></Bill>