<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Bill bill-origin="senate" bill-type="private-public" xml:lang="en" date-time="2026-03-19 11:20:36"><Identification><BillNumber>S-248</BillNumber><Parliament><Session>1</Session><Number>45</Number><RegnalYear><Year-s>3-4</Year-s><Monarch>Charles III</Monarch></RegnalYear><Year-s>2025-2026</Year-s></Parliament><LongTitle>An Act respecting Caribbean Heritage Month</LongTitle><ShortTitle status="unofficial">Caribbean Heritage Month Act</ShortTitle><RunningHead>Caribbean Heritage Month Act</RunningHead><BillHistory><Stages stage="first-reading-senate"><Date><YYYY>2026</YYYY><MM>5</MM><DD>26</DD></Date></Stages></BillHistory><BillSponsor>Senator SENIOR</BillSponsor><BillRefNumber date-time="">4512530</BillRefNumber></Identification><Introduction><Summary><TitleText>SUMMARY</TitleText><Provision><Text>This enactment designates the month of July in each and every year as “Caribbean Heritage Month”.</Text></Provision></Summary><Preamble><Provision language-align="yes" topmarginspacing="-6" pointsize="10"><MarginalNote>Preamble</MarginalNote><Text>Whereas persons of Caribbean origin have been settling in Canada since the late 18th century and today form a significant and vibrant part of Canadian society;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Canadians of Caribbean origin or background have contributed greatly to the success and enrichment of Canada’s economic, social, political and cultural fabric; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas the Parliament of Canada recognizes the longstanding importance of Caribbean heritage to the Canadian nation and that Canada is home to <Keep>numerous</Keep> Caribbean cultural festivals, including the Toronto Caribbean Carnival, a major summer festival inaugurated more than 50 years ago that showcases and promotes the culture and contributions of Canadians of Caribbean origin and has established a <Keep>significant</Keep> presence in the cultural and economic landscape of Canada;</Text></Provision><Provision><Text>Whereas Caribbean culture has influenced several <Keep>aspects</Keep> of modern urban culture, including linguistic, sport, musical and culinary attributes; </Text></Provision><Provision><Text>And whereas the Parliament of Canada wishes to recognize and celebrate the historic contributions that Caribbean Canadians have made and continue to make in building Canadian society;</Text></Provision></Preamble><Enacts><Provision><Text>Now, therefore, His Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Senate and House of Commons of Canada, enacts as follows:</Text></Provision></Enacts></Introduction><Body><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Short Title</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Short title</MarginalNote><Label>1</Label><Text>This Act may be cited as the <Emphasis style="italic">Caribbean Heritage Month Act</Emphasis>.</Text></Section><Heading level="1"><TitleText>Caribbean Heritage Month</TitleText></Heading><Section><MarginalNote>Caribbean Heritage Month</MarginalNote><Label>2</Label><Text>Throughout Canada, in each and every year, the month of July is to be known as “Caribbean Heritage Month”.</Text></Section></Body></Bill>